=Romance of a Twin Flower=
= Romance de una flor gemela =
=Episode 6=
= Episodio 6 =
Mr. Ning.
Sr. Ning.
You know a lot of people here.
Usted conoce a mucha gente aquí.
Is this what the palace looks like?
¿Es así como se ve el palacio?
It's grand.
Es genial.
Don't forget who you are
No olvides quién eres
in front of His Majesty.
frente a Su Majestad.
People don't know about your memory loss.
La gente no sabe de tu pérdida de memoria.
Just stay with me
Solo quédate conmigo
and be careful with your words.
y ten cuidado con tus palabras.
Don't blunder.
No emborrones.
Do you understand?
¿Entiendes?
Mr. Ning.
Sr. Ning.
What kind of
Qué tipo de
relationship
relación
should we pretend to have later?
debemos fingir tener más tarde?
For example, we can be affectionate,
Por ejemplo, podemos ser cariñosos,
or friendly in appearance but estranged at heart,
u amigable en apariencia pero alejado del corazón,
or
o
we can act like enemies.
podemos actuar como enemigos.
I can do either one.
Puedo hacer cualquiera de ellas.
Which one do you want?
¿Cuál quieres?
Mr. Ning.
Sr. Ning.
Yuxuan.
Yuxuan.
I have something to ask you.
Tengo algo que preguntarte.
Never mind.
Nunca importa.
How come you have such good skin?
¿Cómo es que tienes tan buena piel?
Yes, you have such fine skin.
Sí, tienes una piel tan fina.
Look at
Mira
your pale and delicate skin.
tu piel pálida y delicada.
I'm not like you.
No soy como tú.
My face is wrinkled.
Mi cara está arrugada.
- Not at all. - It's not that bad.
- En absoluto. - No es tan malo.
Look, my skin is dark.
Mira, mi piel es oscura.
It does look worse.
Se ve peor.
Oh, no.
Oh, no.
Sisters.
Hermanas.
Mrs. Ning.
Sra. Ning.
Hello, guys.
Hola, chicos.
You all look good.
Todos se ven bien.
I wonder what kind of...
Me pregunto qué clase de...
Sangyu.
Sangyu.
You have the finest skin.
Tienes la piel más fina.
Who are you?
¿Quién eres?
Look at her skin.
Mira su piel.
It's good by nature.
Por naturaleza es bueno.
General Tao?
¿General Tao?
Sangyu.
Sangyu.
I arranged the banquet today.
Preparé el banquete hoy.
How's it?
¿Cómo está?
It's good.
Es bueno.
I'm glad you like it.
Me alegro de que te guste.
I haven't finished yet.
Aún no he terminado.
What kind of face cream
¿Qué tipo de crema facial
do you use every day?
uses todos los días?
Sangyu, you should take your seat.
Sangyu, deberías tomar tu asiento.
I have something to do here.
Tengo algo que hacer aquí.
Just do what you got to do.
Solo haz lo que tienes que hacer.
If you don't mind.
Si no te importa.
I would like to recommend
Me gustaría recomendar
the face cream I use to you.
la crema facial que utilizo.
Look at my skin.
Mira mi piel.
Isn't it pretty good?
¿No es bastante buena?
Sangyu.
Sangyu.
- The banquet is about to start. - It works very well.
- El banquete está a punto de empezar. - Recibe muy bien.
Let's go.
Vamos.
Wait for me.
Espérame.
I'll be back later.
Volveré más tarde.
Okay?
¿De acuerdo?
Okay.
Está bien.
Make sure you wait for me.
Asegúrese de que me esperas.
Sangyu.
Sangyu.
I wonder what kind of face cream
Me pregunto qué tipo de crema facial
Mrs. Ning is using.
sra. Ning está usando.
Yes, it worked pretty well.
Sí, funcionó bastante bien.
Sangyu, please.
Sangyu, por favor.
You're a neat person.
Eres una persona genial.
I was afraid you wouldn't be used to it,
Tenía miedo de que no estuvieras acostumbrado a eso,
so I came here early
así que vine aquí temprano
and cleaned it up.
y lo limpié.
Yuxuan is just like me.
Yuxuan es igual que yo.
As a man,
Como hombre,
he doesn't care about such things.
no le importan tales cosas.
Thank you.
Gracias.
What? Say it again.
¿Qué? Dilo otra vez.
General Tao.
General Tao.
Thank you.
Gracias.
Wait, are you thanking me?
Espera, ¿me estás dando las gracias?
Shouldn't I?
¿No debería?
Of course not.
Claro que no.
You're supposed to pick on me
Se supone que tienes que buscarme
for not cleaning it well
por no limpiarlo bien
and for not doing it the way you want.
y por no hacerlo como quieres.
That's what you should do.
Eso es lo que deberías hacer.
I don't think so.
No lo creo.
You must be joking, General Tao.
Debes estar bromeando, General Tao.
No, I'm not joking.
No, No estoy bromeando.
It's just that you've always been like this before.
Es solo que siempre has estado como este antes.
Before?
¿Antes?
What was I like before?
¿Qué me gustaba antes?
You never used to smile at me.
Nunca solían sonreírme.
You'd just dismiss me, pick on me,
Me rechazarías,
and even hit me when you had a slight disagreement with me.
e incluso golpearme cuando un pequeño desacuerdo conmigo.
Have you forgotten all that?
¿Has olvidado todo eso?
We've been like this
Hemos sido así
since we first went to school together.
desde que fuimos a la escuela juntos.
School?
¿Escuela?
Have I always been like this?
¿Yo siempre he sido así?
Yeah.
Sí.
Let me think about it.
Déjame pensar en ello.
Do it.
Hazlo.
I'll take my time to think about it.
Tomaré mi tiempo para pensar en ello.
(Is there something wrong)
(¿Hay algo mal)
(with this guy?)
(con este tipo?)
(Why does he want to be treated that way?)
(¿Por qué quiere ser tratado de esa manera?)
Yes, I remember now.
Sí, lo recuerdo ahora.
That's true.
Eso es cierto.
I remember now. I...
Lo recuerdo ahora.
No, no.
No, no.
You've changed.
Has cambiado.
You're making me uncomfortable.
Me estás haciendo incómoda.
Is it because
Es porque
Ning Yuxuan set rules for you
ning Yuxuan establece reglas para usted
and that's why you have your wings clipped?
y por eso tienes tus alas cortadas?
We went to the same school.
Fuimos a la misma escuela.
You don't have to be so polite to me.
No tienes que ser tan cortés conmigo.
No, no.
No,
It has nothing to do with him.
no tiene nada que ver con él.
Maybe it's because I...
Tal vez sea porque yo...
I've changed.
He cambiado.
You've changed?
¿Has cambiado?
Yes.
Sí.
Can you
¿Puede usted
change back
vuelve a cambiarte
and hit me?
y golpearme?
Or you can scold me.
O puedes regodearme.
That's not necessary.
No es necesario.
I can't do that.
No puedo hacer eso.
No, no, you can.
No, puedes.
I can't.
No puedo.
It's inappropriate.
Es inapropiado.
It's very appropriate.
Es muy apropiado.
No, no.
No, no.
There is nothing inappropriate.
No hay nada inapropiado.
His Majesty
Su Majestad
may be here any minute.
puede estar aquí cualquier minuto.
Why don't you go and greet him?
¿Por qué no vas a saludarlo?
Otherwise, it would be impolite.
De otra manera, sería descortés.
Well, Sangyu, have a seat first.
Bueno, Sangyu, tome asiento primero.
I'll see you later.
Te veré más tarde.
Okay.
Está bien.
By the way, Qin.
Por cierto, Qin.
There's one thing I don't understand.
Hay una cosa que no entiendo.
A few days ago,
Hace unos días,
I took a few days off because of typhoid fever.
me tomé unos días libres debido a la fiebre tifoidea.
Why does His Majesty
¿Por qué Su Majestad
insist that I must come?
insiste en que debo venir?
The Longxiang Army won the battle.
El Ejército de Longxiang ganó la batalla.
His Majesty wants to reward the meritorious officials.
Su Majestad quiere premiar los meritorios funcionarios.
Ling Jianxing specifically mentioned
Ling Jianxing menciona específicamente
that you should be present with your wife.
que deberías estar presente con tu esposa.
You must be more careful.
Debes tener más cuidado.
Consul Ling.
Consul Ling.
Here comes Lord Tan!
¡Aquí viene Lord Tan!
Mr. Ning.
Sr. Ning.
Mr. Ling.
Sr. Ling.
Are you feeling better now?
¿Se siente mejor ahora?
Thank you for your concern, Mr. Ling.
Gracias por su preocupación, Sr. Ling.
I have recovered.
Me he recuperado.
Mr. Ling.
Sr. Ling.
You should also take good care of yourself.
También deberías cuidarte bien.
Please.
Por favor.
My dear, have a seat.
Querida, toma asiento.
Here comes His Majesty!
¡Aquí viene Su Majestad!
(Beautiful Days and Nights with Flowers and the Moon)
(Días hermosos y noches con Flores y la Luna)
Greetings, Your Majesty.
Saludos, Su Majestad.
You may rise.
Usted puede levantarse.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
Gracias, Su Majestad.
Sit down.
Siente.
Is he the Emperor?
¿Es él el emperador?
Uncle.
Tío.
Today I'm rewarding the meritorious officials,
Hoy estoy recompensando los funcionarios meritorios,
and you can
y puedes
meet many of
conocer a muchos
your old brothers here.
tus hermanos mayores aquí.
I'm already an old man.
Ya soy un anciano.
I'm afraid
Me temo que
they have forgotten me.
se han olvidado de mí.
Back then, our country was in turmoil.
En ese entonces, nuestro país estaba en estado de agitación.
The late emperor was seriously ill.
El último emperador estaba gravemente enfermo.
Among all the Imperial Guards,
Entre todos los guardias imperiales,
we couldn't even gather
ni siquiera podíamos reunir
500 cavalrymen.
500 jinetes.
Things are different now.
Ahora las cosas son diferentes.
The army split up first and then made a joint attack,
El ejército se dividió primero y luego realizó un ataque conjunto,
and returned in triumph.
y regresó triunfante.
Your Majesty,
Su Majestad,
the world is all yours now.
el mundo es todo tuyo ahora.
Uncle, it was you who acted as regent when our country was in danger
Tío, fuiste tú quien actuó como regente cuando nuestro país estaba en peligro
and reorganized the armies.
y reorganizaron los ejércitos.
When the enemy was bearing down in force,
Cuando el enemigo se abalanzaba,
you took me on horseback
me llevaste a caballo
to inspect the Imperial Guards.
para inspeccionar a la Guardia Imperial.
At that time,
En ese momento,
I didn't know how to ride a horse.
no sabía montar a caballo.
The good thing is I learned it later,
Lo bueno es que lo aprendí más tarde,
so that I didn't have to
así que no tuve que
let someone control the reins.
deja que alguien controle las riendas.
Please sit down, Uncle.
Siéntese, tío.
You're also here, Marquis Moyu.
También estás aquí, Marquis Moyu.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Si, Su Majestad.
How is your health?
¿Cómo está tu salud?
Thank you for your concern.
Gracias por su preocupación.
I have recovered.
Me he recuperado.
Have a seat.
Toma asiento.
Everyone.
Todos.
Today is a day of celebration.
Hoy es un día de celebración.
We'll share happiness together.
Compartimos la felicidad juntos.
There is no need to be too formal.
No hay necesidad de ser demasiado formal.
Let's begin.
Comencemos.
Start the music
Empieza la música
and the dance.
y el baile.
This is a fruitful trip.
Este es un viaje fructífero.
They are all my potential customers.
Todos son mis clientes potenciales.
Dear.
Querida.
Watch your manners.
Mira tus modales.
What did I do?
¿Qué hice?
Do I have to
¿Tengo que
sit here
sentarse aquí
like a stone?
como una piedra?
My legs are a little sore.
Mis piernas tienen un poco de dolor.
Rub my legs.
Frote mis piernas.
We have to act like
Tenemos que actuar como
we're a lovely couple
somos una pareja encantadora
in front of His Majesty.
frente a Su Majestad.
It's good for you
Es bueno para ti
to let others see
para que otros vean
that we have a wonderful relationship. You silly man.
que tenemos una maravillosa relación. Tonto.
Hurry up.
Date prisa.
Here.
Aquí.
Right here.
Aquí mismo.
Come on.
Vamos.
What are you doing?
¿Qué estás haciendo?
Dear, remember,
Querido, recuerda,
I won't be threatened by anyone.
no seré amenazado por nadie.
Mr. Ning, Mrs. Ning.
Sr. Ning, Sra. Ning.
This is Mr. Ling.
Este es el Sr. Ling.
Nice to meet you.
Encantado de conocerte.
It's rare to see you
Es raro verte
show up with Mrs. Ning.
ve con la Sra. Ning.
You must be in a good mood today.
Debes estar de buen humor hoy.
Yeah.
Sí,
No wonder.
no es de extrañar.
No wonder what?
No me pregunto qué?
I thought Mr. Ning would bring
Pensé que el Sr. Ning traería
his newly married wife.
su esposa recién casada.
I didn't expect the First Lady
No esperaba a la Primera Dama
to be so beautiful.
para ser tan hermoso.
I see.
Ya veo.
Mr. Ning.
Sr. Ning.
I heard that your newly married wife
Escuché que su esposa recién casada
is gentle and virtuous.
es amable y virtuosa.
You made us envious of you.
Nos hiciste envidioso de ti.
Mr. Ling.
Sr. Ling.
As the old saying goes,
Como dice el viejo dicho,
one should raise a family first before he governs the country.
primero deberíamos criar a una familia antes de que gobierne el país.
You're not young anymore.
Ya no eres joven.
You should think about
Deberías pensar en
finding yourself a wife.
encontrarte una esposa.
No matter how beautiful the women are in the brothel,
No importa lo hermoso las mujeres están en el burdel,
they're still passing clouds.
todavía están pasando nubes.
He looks like a decent man.
Parece un hombre decente.
Why is he so mean?
¿Por qué es tan malo?
Do you have a feud with him?
¿Tenés un feudo con él?
Do you?
¿Tú?
I see.
Ya veo.
Did you steal his woman?
¿Robaste a su mujer?
That must be the reason.
Esa debe ser la razón.
No wonder.
No es extraño.
That's how he is
Es así
at the school.
en la escuela.
Just get used to it.
Solo acostumbrarte.
Is he your schoolmate?
¿Es tu compañero de escuela?
Yeah.
Sí.
Your schoolmate is also strange.
Tu compañero de colegio también es extraño.
I'm not feeling unfair anymore.
Ya no me siento injusto.
Thank you.
Gracias.
What's wrong? Does the wound hurt again?
¿Qué pasa? ¿Te duele la herida otra vez?
Are you okay?
¿Estás bien?
I'll be going out for a while.
Voy a salir por un tiempo.
Dear.
Querido.
This is the Imperial Palace, not my residence.
Este es el palacio Imperial, no mi residencia.
Don't wander around.
No vuelvas.
I...
Yo...
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
For this grand occasion,
Para esta gran ocasión,
I specially brought
traje especialmente
a batch of fresh crabs from Haifang
un lote de cangrejos frescos de Haifang
to serve as a wine accompaniment for you and other officials.
para servir como acompañamiento de vino para ti y otros funcionarios.
Ling.
Maruca.
How did you manage to transport the crabs
¿Cómo lograste transportar los cangrejos
all the way from Haifang to the capital?
desde Haifang hasta la capital?
I first transported the crabs
Primero transporté los cangrejos
to the port nearest to the capital,
al puerto más cercano a la capital,
and put them in barrels
y los puso en barriles
filled with seawater,
lleno de agua de mar,
and then rushed all the way here
y luego corrió todo el camino aquí
for 600 miles.
durante 600 millas.
The crabs are still alive
Los cangrejos siguen vivos
and tasty.
y sabroso.
You're resourceful indeed.
Eres ingenioso de hecho.
All right.
Está bien.
Bring the crabs
Trae los cangrejos
so that all of you
para que todos ustedes
can enjoy them.
puede divertirlos.
I thought they were cooked in some other way.
Pensé que estaban cocinados de alguna otra forma.
If His Majesty
Si Su Majestad
enjoys the food,
disfruta de la comida,
we must enjoy it, too.
debemos disfrutarlo también.
Do you remember?
¿Recuerdas?
Everyone.
Todos.
Let's have a taste.
Vamos a probar.
Mr. Ning. Mrs. Ning.
Sr. Ning. Sra. Ning.
Why aren't you eating?
¿Por qué no estás comiendo?
Have you never had crabs before
Nunca has tenido cangrejos antes
and you don't know how to peel them?
y no sabes cómo pelarlos?
It's okay.
Está bien.
I'll have someone peel them for you.
Voy a tener a alguien pelarlos para ti.
Here.
Aquí.
That won't be necessary.
Eso no será necesario.
Dear, look.
Querida, mira.
Actually, this is not the best way
En realidad, esta no es la mejor forma
to cook crabs.
cocinar cangrejos.
What do you mean?
¿Qué quieres decir?
Let me tell you
Déjame decirte
how I used to eat crabs.
cómo solía comer cangrejos.
Marinate the crabs in a mixture of
Marinar los cangrejos en una mezcla de
one catty of water, four taels of salt,
un poco de agua, cuatro taels de sal,
and some white wine.
y un poco de vino blanco,
It would taste
sabría
amazing.
increíble.
You know what, next time,
Ya sabes, la próxima vez,
I'm gonna...
voy a...
Dear.
Querido.
His Majesty is still here.
Su Majestad sigue aquí.
You'd better behave yourself.
Será mejor que te comportes.
Mr. Ning, are you stopping Mrs. Ning from eating
Sr. Ning, ¿se detiene sra. Ning de comer
because you're afraid she might eat too quickly?
porque tienes miedo podría comer demasiado rápido?
It's okay.
Está bien.
Let's give
Vamos a dar
Mrs. Ning one more crab.
sra. Ning un cangrejo más.
If she does
Si lo hace
like them,
como ellos,
I can also have someone deliver them to your mansion.
también puedo tener a alguien llévales a tu mansión.
After all, not everyone
Después de todo, no todos
is able to enjoy such a delicacy.
es capaz de disfrutar de tal delicadeza.
That won't be necessary, Mr. Ling.
No será necesario, Sr. Ling.
Look.
Mira.
You've gone to great lengths
Has ido muy lejos
to transport these crabs 600 miles
para transportar estos cangrejos 600 kilómetros
from Haifang to the capital.
de Haifang a la capital.
It required financial, material, and human resources,
Requería recursos financieros, materiales, y recursos humanos,
which must have cost you a lot.
que te debe haber costado mucho.
Those who know
Aquellos que saben
might see your loyalty to His Majesty,
podría ver su lealtad a Su Majestad,
but those who don't know
pero aquellos que no saben
might think you're wasting manpower and money.
podría pensar que estás perdiendo mano de obra y dinero.
Mrs. Ning, you're being impudent!
Sra. Ning, ¡estás siendo impúdica!
You're not only satirizing me.
No solo me estás satirizando.
You're also satirizing His Majesty!
¡También estás satirizando a Su Majestad!
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
I...
Yo...
My wife has no such intention.
Mi esposa no tiene tal intención.
Mr. Ling, don't overthink.
Sr. Ling, no exageres.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
Mr. Ling has misunderstood me.
El Sr. Ling me ha entendido mal.
I just want to tell him
Solo quiero decirle
there is another way to cook crabs
hay otra forma de cocinar cangrejos
that is less troublesome
eso es menos problemático
and can also preserve
y también puede preservar
the freshness of the seafood.
la frescura del marisco.
Do you know
¿Sabes
any other way?
de cualquier otra manera?
Of course, there is a method
Por supuesto, existe un método
called "marinating the crab".
llamado "marinando el cangrejo".
- Marinating... - Dear.
- marinando... - Mi amor.
What is this method of
¿Cuál es este método de
"marinating the crab"?
"Marinando el cangrejo"?
If you're interested,
Si estás interesado,
I'll do it for you
lo haré por ti
right now.
ahora mismo.
Okay. Go ahead.
Está bien. Adelante.
Your Majesty, as the saying goes,
Su Majestad, como dice el dicho,
"It would be a waste of eyes not to visit Mount Lu,
"Sería un desperdicio de ojos no visitar el monte Lu,
and a waste of stomach
y un desperdicio de estómago
not to eat crabs."
no comer cangrejos ".
When it comes to crabs,
En cuanto a los cangrejos,
the key is
la clave es
freshness.
frescura.
So,
Así que
the way I marinate the crabs today
la forma en que marinar los cangrejos hoy
can preserve the freshness of the crabs
puede preservar la frescura de los cangrejos
to the greatest extent.
en su mayor medida.
Okay.
Está bien.
Next,
Siguiente,
it needs to be
tiene que
marinated for a while.
marinado por un tiempo.
Go and wait.
Ve a esperar.
Yes.
Sí.
Don't be in a hurry.
No tengas prisa.
Just a moment.
Un momento.
It's done.
Ya está.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
Are you sure it's edible?
¿Estás seguro de que es comestible?
If His Majesty
Si Su Majestad
gets sick from it,
se enferma de ella,
being beheaded nine times
decapitado nueve veces
is not gonna be enough.
no va a ser suficiente.
Don't worry.
No te preocupes.
How is it?
¿Cómo está?
Are you asking me
¿Me estás pidiendo
to eat the raw crabs?
para comer los cangrejos crudos?
Marinated crabs should be eaten raw.
Los cangrejos marinados se deben comer crudos.
That would taste the best.
Sabría bien.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
I've never heard of eating raw crabs before.
Nunca he oído hablar de como cangrejos crudos antes.
As the divinely ordained ruler,
Como gobernante divino,
you shouldn't eat raw food.
no deberías comer comida cruda.
Mr. Ling.
Sr. Ling.
Don't take your ignorance
No aceptes tu ignorancia
for your personality, okay?
para tu personalidad, ¿okey?
How is it?
¿Cómo está?
It's fresh.
Es fresco.
Great.
Genial.
Everyone.
Todos.
Come and have a taste of
Ven a probar
Mrs. Ning's crabs.
cangrejos de la señora Ning.
Okay!
¡Está bien!
Here.
Aquí.
Share them.
Comparte.
Have a try.
Intenta.
I saved it for you.
Lo guardé para ti.
It's delicious.
Es delicioso.
I...
Yo...
Mrs. Ning.
Sra. Ning.
If Mr. Ning doesn't want to eat it,
Si el Sr. Ning no quiere comerlo,
I'll have one more.
tendré una más.
This is the most delicious thing in the world.
Esto es lo más delicioso en el mundo.
I'm glad you like it.
Me alegro de que te guste.
It's delicious.
Es delicioso.
Nie Sangyu.
Nie Sangyu.
Come over and speak to me.
Ven a hablar conmigo.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
I want to ask you something.
Quiero preguntarte algo.
How did you know about
¿Cómo supiste
this way of cooking crabs?
esta forma de cocinar cangrejos?
I don't know how.
No sé cómo.
But
Pero
the way of marinating crabs
la manera de marinar cangrejos
is easy and efficient,
es fácil y eficiente,
and it can preserve the freshness of the crabs
y puede preservar la frescura de los cangrejos
to the greatest extent.
en su mayor parte.
Right?
¿Sí?
Your method is much better
Tu método es mucho mejor
than Ling's.
que el de Ling.
I have one more thing to ask you.
Tengo una cosa más que preguntarle.
Do you have any other
¿Tienes alguna otra
new and interesting ways of cooking?
nuevas e interesantes formas de cocinar?
I do.
Sí.
Come up and tell me.
Ven y dime.
Okay.
Está bien.
Nie Sangyu, don't be rude!
Nie Sangyu, ¡no seas descortés!
Mr. Ning.
Sr. Ning.
Is this how you train your wife?
¿Es así como entrenas a tu esposa?
Shut up.
Cállate.
Go ahead and tell me.
Adelante y dime.
Well, Your Majesty,
Bueno, Su Majestad,
let me give you an example
déjame darte un ejemplo
of tofu.
de tofu.
There are so many different ways to cook tofu:
Hay tantas diferentes formas de cocinar tofu:
soft tofu, frozen tofu,
tofu blando, tofu congelado,
southern tofu, northern tofu,
tofu meridional, tofu septentrional,
braised tofu, fried tofu,
tofu asado, tofu frito,
sizzling tofu,
tofu colimado,
and Yangzhou-style tofu, etc.
y tofu estilo Yangzhou-, etc.
You can summon me
Puedes convocarme
whenever you want to try them,
cuando quieras probarlos,
and I'll cook for you.
y voy a cocinar para ti.
Okay.
Está bien.
Great.
Genial.
Is there anything else?
¿Hay algo más?
Yes.
Sí.
There is a kind of medicinal wine
Hay una especie de vino medicinal
made from seahorses
hechos de caballos de mar
that nourishes yin and invigorates yang.
que nutre yin y revitaliza el yang.
- Sangyu. - The wine...
- Sangyu. - El vino...
Come down now.
Ven ahora.
Did I say too much?
¿He dicho demasiado?
Ning.
Durante.
You married
Usted se casó
a truly sincere and virtuous lady.
una dama auténticamente sincera y virtuosa.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
Gracias, Su Majestad.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
Today's banquet
Banquete de hoy
is to celebrate the great victory of the army.
es celebrar la gran victoria del ejército.
I have an idea.
Tengo una idea.
I would like to compete with Mr. Ning in a sword fight
Me gustaría competir con el Sr. Ning en una pelea a espada
to liven up the atmosphere.
calentar la atmósfera.
Okay.
Está bien.
I've never seen
Nunca he visto
you two competing in swordsmanship.
ustedes dos compitiendo en espado.
I don't think it's a good idea, Your Majesty.
No creo que sea una buena idea, su Majestad.
My husband
Mi marido.
has just recovered from a serious illness.
Se acaba de recuperar de una enfermedad grave.
He is not agile enough.
No es lo suficientemente ágil.
So...
Así que
Mrs. Ning is concerned about her husband.
a la Sra. Ning le preocupa su marido.
Since Ning
Desde Ning
has not yet fully recovered,
todavía no se ha recuperado completamente,
let's skip the swordplay.
evitemos el juego de espada.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
Gracias, Su Majestad.
When His Majesty was young
Cuando Su Majestad era joven
and I acted as regent,
y actué como regente,
I was busy with state affairs.
estaba ocupado con asuntos de estado.
Although I was sick.
Aunque estaba enfermo.
I dared not slack off at all.
No me atreví a relajarme en absoluto.
Now
Ahora
I'm not like the young people.
no soy como los jóvenes.
Pour the wine.
Derrama el vino.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
I'm willing to compete in swordsmanship
Estoy dispuesto a competir en tiro
on behalf of Mr. Ning.
en nombre del Sr. Ning.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
I'm willing to compete in swordsmanship.
Estoy dispuesto a competir en puntería.
But you can't.
Pero no puedes.
Okay.
Está bien.
Then we'll see
Entonces veremos
how good you two are at swordsmanship.
qué tan bueno son tus dos
I can't let Ling Jianxing know
no puedo permitir que Ling Jianxing sepa
that I'm hurt.
que estoy herida.
But your injury...
Pero su lesión
Mr. Ling, how are we going to compete?
sr. Ling, ¿cómo vamos a competir?
It's simple.
Es sencillo.
You and I each plant a flag,
Tú y yo plantamos una bandera,
and whoever takes the other's flag first
y quien tome primero la bandera del otro
is the winner.
es el ganador.
Okay.
Está bien.
Mr. Ning, since you've just recovered from your illness,
Sr. Ning, ya que acabas de recuperado de su enfermedad,
I'll let you make three moves first.
te dejaré hacer tres movimientos primero.
No need.
No es necesario.
Well, then please
Bueno, entonces por favor
use your full strength.
utilice toda su fuerza.
Mr. Ning, show me what you got.
Sr. Ning, enséñame lo que tienes.
Fight me as if I'm your enemy!
¡Enfréntame como si fuera tu enemigo!
Don't push it.
No lo empujes.
Mr. Ning.
Sr. Ning.
I've heard that your swordsmanship is unparalleled,
He oído que tu salvajismo no tiene paralelo,
but it seems like it's not that great.
pero parece que no es tan genial.
Ning Yuxuan!
Ning Yuxuan!
Well...
Bueno...
Be careful!
¡Cuidado!
You...
Tú...
Are you okay?
¿Estás bien?
Your Majesty, we won!
¡Su Majestad! ¡Ganamos!
I can't let His Majesty
No puedo permitir a Su Majestad
find out about my injury.
averigua acerca de mi lesión.
Mr. Ning.
Sr. Ning.
You can't live
No puedes vivir
without Mrs. Ning, can you?
sin la Sra. Ning, ¿verdad?
You even relied on her to win the competition.
Incluso confiaste en ella para ganar la competición.
It's unfair for the two of you
Es injusto para ustedes dos
to fight against me alone.
para luchar contra mí solo.
You took advantage of his illness.
Usted se aprovechó de su enfermedad.
How despicable of you.
Qué detestable de ti.
You...
Tú...
Nie Sangyu.
Nie Sangyu.
Come forward. I'll speak to you.
Adelante. Hablaré contigo.
Stay five steps away from His Majesty
Quédate cinco pasos de Su Majestad
and stand there.
y quédate ahí.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
We won.
Ganamos.
Nie Sangyu.
Nie Sangyu.
You are the daughter of a general.
Eres la hija de un general.
They were competing in a sword fight.
Estaban compitiendo en una pelea de espada.
Don't you know
¿No sabes
the competition rules?
las reglas de competencia?
Ning.
Ning.
I'll rule against you
Voy a gobernar contra ti
this time.
esta vez.
But...
Pero...
Do you have any complaints?
¿Tienes alguna queja?
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
I have no complaints.
No tengo quejas.
However,
Sin embargo,
I saw that you and your wife
vI que usted y su esposa
have love and support for each other,
se aman y apoyan mutuamente,
which has deeply moved me.
lo que me ha conmovido profundamente.
If all husbands and wives in the world
Si todos los maridos y esposas del mundo
could be like you,
podría ser como tú,
then all families would be at peace,
entonces todas las familias estarían en paz,
and the nation would be at peace.
y la nación estaría en paz.
Nie Sangyu.
Nie Sangyu.
I've decided to make you the Second-rank Lady with Imperial Mandate.
He decidido hacerte la dama de segundo rango con mandato Imperial.
From now on, you two will be the model
A partir de ahora, ustedes dos serán el modelo
for all couples in the world.
para todas las parejas en el mundo.
What do you think?
¿Qué crees?
I don't think it's appropriate, Your Majesty.
No creo que sea adecuado, su Majestad.
No,
No,
that's not what I meant.
eso no es lo que quería decir.
You don't have to do this, Your Majesty.
No tienes que hacer esto, Su Majestad.
- You're too kind. - Nie Sangyu.
- Eres demasiado amable. - Nie Sangyu.
You must thank His Majesty
Debes agradecer a Su Majestad
for the title bestowed upon you.
por el título que se le ha concedido.
No, Your Majesty.
No, Su Majestad.
I really don't...
Realmente no...
Dear, bow to His Majesty.
Querido, inclínate a Su Majestad.
I don't mean that.
No me refiero a eso.
Bow now.
Inclínate ahora.
You...
Usted...
Thank you for your grace, Your Majesty.
Gracias por su gracia, Su Majestad.
You're a titled lady now.
Eres una dama con título ahora.
Why are you still so sullen?
¿Por qué todavía estás tan aburrida?
If I had to choose between being granted a title
Si tuviera que elegir entre obtención de un título
or getting a divorce,
o divorciarme,
I would rather not have this title.
prefiero no tener este título.
It's done. Don't move.
Ha terminado. No se mueva.
I've just applied the medicine to you.
Acabo de aplicarte la medicina.
You know what, the dress for titled ladies
¿Sabes qué?, el vestido para chicas tituladas
does look valuable.
parece valioso.
I think we could sell it
Creo que lo podríamos vender
for a lot of money.
por mucho dinero.
Yeah.
Sí.
Unfortunately, selling the things bestowed by the emperor
Lamentablemente, vender las cosas otorgado por el emperador
is a capital offense.
es una ofensa capital.
I'm just saying.
Solo digo.
Do you really think
¿De verdad crees que
I like that dress?
¿Me gusta ese vestido?
Now I'm a titled lady,
Ahora soy una dama con título,
wouldn't that
no sería
improve
mejora
my reputation?
mi reputación?
I guess.
Supongo.
Then wouldn't it
Entonces, ¿no sería
be a boost for my business?
sería un impulso para mi negocio?
Scar Recovering Cream with Imperial Mandate.
Crema de recuperación de cicatrices con mandato Imperial.
It sounds expensive.
Suena caro.
But we're getting a divorce.
Pero estamos en divorcio.
Only the wife of an official
Solo a la esposa de un funcionario
can be granted with imperial mandate.
solo se le concede un mandato imperial.
I think
Creo que
we can't rush this.
no podemos apresurarnos.
You're not in a hurry to get a divorce, right?
No tienes prisa para divorciarte, ¿verdad?
I think
Creo que
we need
necesitamos
a cooling-off period.
un período de enfriamiento.
It's good for everyone.
Es bueno para todos.
I saved your life today.
He salvado tu vida hoy.
We can postpone the divorce for a few days, right?
Podemos aplazar el divorcio durante unos días, ¿verdad?
Sure.
Claro.
I'll hold a tea party here
Celebraré una fiesta de té aquí
in a few days
en unos días
to celebrate
para celebrar
that you're a titled lady now
que eres una dama con título ahora
and express gratitude to His Majesty.
y expresar su gratitud a Su Majestad.
Prepare well.
Prepárate bien.
Do we need to go through all this trouble?
¿Tenemos que pasar por todos estos problemas?
Just bear with it.
Solo aguántalo.
We have to follow the rules.
Tenemos que seguir las reglas.
Okay.
Está bien.
We don't have to get a divorce,
No tenemos que divorciarnos,
but we have to keep track of our accounts clearly.
pero tenemos que hacer un seguimiento de nuestras cuentas claramente.
Okay. What accounts?
Está bien. ¿Qué cuentas?
The accounts of what we did as a couple.
Las cuentas de lo que hicimos como pareja.
This is it.
Esto es todo.
Before we get a formal divorce,
Antes de tener un divorcio formal,
we will each spend our own money
gastaremos nuestro propio dinero
and keep track of the accounts.
y seguir la pista de las cuentas.
Watch carefully.
Cuidado.
Each bead here
Cada talón aquí
represents 100 taels.
representa 100 taels.
The blue beads are yours.
Las cuentas azules son tuyas.
The red ones are mine.
Los rojos son míos.
Starting from the day
Empezando desde el día
I asked for a divorce,
pedí el divorcio,
whoever does something nice
quien haga algo bueno
for the other
por el otro
will put a bead
pondrá un perno
into this box.
en esta caja.
And whoever does something wrong to the other
Y quien hace algo malo al otro
will take out a bead
sacará una barba
from the box.
de la caja.
We'll settle the accounts at the day of divorce.
Liquidaremos las cuentas en el día del divorcio.
Whoever has more beads in the box
Quien tiene más cuentas en la caja
can take the money.
puede llevarse el dinero.
I'll go first.
Iré primero.
I sewed up your wound today.
Hoy he secado su herida.
One bead for me.
Un cuentas para mí.
I applied medicine for you today.
He aplicado medicina para ti hoy.
I...
Yo...
They are the same thing.
Son la misma cosa.
I also hid your injury from others.
También escondí tu lesión a otros.
I'll let you put two beads in the box
Te dejaré poner dos cuentas en la caja
for these three things.
para estas tres cosas.
You're so stingy.
Eres tan tacaño.
I got the medicine for you today.
Tengo la medicina para ti hoy.
One bead for me.
Una barra para mí.
I didn't get the medicine today.
No recibí la medicina hoy.
It doesn't count.
No cuenta.
I was made Second-rank Lady with Imperial Mandate today
Me hicieron dama de segundo rango con mandato Imperial hoy
which brought honor to your family.
que trajo honor a su familia.
This should count as two beads.
Esto debe contar como dos cuentas.
But,
Pero,
you almost
casi
exposed my injury today
expuso mi herida hoy
and caused unnecessary attention,
y causó una atención innecesaria,
so I'll subtract one bead.
así que reste una hoja.
I...
Yo...
Fine. It's your turn.
Bien. Es tu turno.
I got you the meal standard of
Te llevé el estándar de comida de
five dishes and one soup at the Reflection Pavilion.
cinco platos y una sopa en el Pabellón de Reflexión.
It was for you.
Fue para ti.
I don't care.
No me importa.
I...
Yo...
Fine.
Bien.
What's the second thing?
¿Qué es lo segundo?
I'll tell you when I remember.
Se lo diré cuando lo recuerde.
Based on your current behavior,
Basado en su comportamiento actual,
the day I leave your mansion
el día que salga de su mansión
will be the day I get rich.
será el día en que me haga rica.
Nie Sangyu.
Nie Sangyu.
I've underestimated you.
Te subestimé.
The Ning family
La familia Ning
actually has a titled lady now.
en realidad tiene una dama con título ahora.
You wicked woman. You don't deserve it.
Mujer malvada. No lo mereces.
Mr. Ling, don't be mad.
Sr. Ling, no estés loco.
This woman suddenly showed up
Esta mujer apareció en la nada
and it was truly unexpected.
y fue verdaderamente inesperado.
When I was competing with Ning Yuxuan,
Cuando yo competía con Ning Yuxuan,
his footsteps were light
sus pasos eran claros
with no strength.
sin fuerzas.
He must have been seriously injured.
Debe haber sido herido de gravedad.
Go and find out
Ve a buscarlo
who hurt him.
que le hizo daño.
Yes.
Sí.
I'll be on it.
Estaré en ello.
If my guess is correct,
Si mi suposición es correcta,
Ning Yuxuan,
con Yuxuan,
your injury
su lesión
must be related to the bandits.
debe estar relacionado con los bandidos.
His Majesty has repeatedly forbidden
Su Majestad ha prohibido repetidamente
unauthorized investigations of the bandits.
investigaciones no autorizadas de los bandidos.
If this is true,
Si esto es cierto,
Ning Yuxuan,
con Yuxuan,
you can only blame it on yourself.
solo puedes culparlo a ti mismo.
Muxu.
Muxu.
How much do you think
¿Cuánto crees que
the dress for titled ladies is worth?
el vestido de las damas con título vale la pena?
It was made by the Emperor's order.
Se hizo por orden del emperador.
It must be worth a thousand taels of silver.
Debe valer mil taels de plata.
No.
No.
In my eyes,
En mis ojos,
this means countless gold.
esto significa un incontable oro.
Countless gold?
¿Incontables de oro?
How much silver do we still have?
¿Cuánto plata todavía tenemos?
I counted it yesterday.
Lo conté ayer.
There are only 280 taels of silver left.
Solo quedan 280 taels de plata.
That's enough.
Eso es suficiente.
We'll use
Usaremos
50 taels
50 taels
among the 280 taels,
entre los 280 taels,
no, 100 taels,
no, 100 taels,
to host a banquet
organizar un banquete
to celebrate that I was granted with imperial mandate.
para celebrar que me concedieron con mandato imperial.
100 taels?
100 taels?
That's right.
Es cierto.
Isn't it too much?
¿No es demasiado?
No.
No.
The celebration
La celebración
must be decorated
debe decorarse
with the most beautiful flowers
con las flores más bellas
and the most luxurious decorations.
y las decoraciones más lujosas.
Make sure to serve
Asegúrese de servir
the most expensive drinks and snacks.
las bebidas más caras y aperitivos.
I'll invite all the royal relatives
Invitaré a todos los parientes reales
and nobles in the capital
y nobles en la capital
and I'll
y yo
mingle with them
mezclar con ellos
as Second-rank Lady with Imperial Mandate.
como dama de segundo rango con mandato Imperial.
And then...
Y luego...
Your Ladyship.
Su señoría.
Nanny Liu.
Niñera Liu.
Congratulations.
Felicitaciones.
You can move back to the Rose Garden.
Puedes volver al Jardín de las Rosas.
Really?
¿En serio?
His Lordship said so.
Su Señoría lo dijo.
Please move back to the Rose Garden today.
Vuelve, por favor al Jardín de rosas hoy.
He said that?
¿Dijo eso?
Move back to the Rose Garden.
Vuelve al Jardín de las Rosas.
But I think
Pero creo que
it's nice to live here.
es bueno vivir aquí.
Go back and tell him
Vuelve y dilo
I don't want to move.
no quiero moverme.
Your Ladyship.
Su señoría.
You are
Eres
Second-rank Lady with Imperial Mandate.
dama de segundo rango con mandato Imperial.
It's inappropriate for you
Es inapropiado para ti
to live in the Reflection Pavilion now.
vivir en el Pabellón de Reflexión ahora.
I think it's appropriate.
Creo que es apropiado.
Look at my Reflection Pavilion now.
Mira mi Pabellón de Reflexión ahora.
I'm living well here.
Vivo bien aquí.
This is no longer
Esto no es ya
the old Reflection Pavilion
el viejo Pabellón de Reflexión
with insects and snakes.
con insectos y serpientes.
I think it's good to live here.
Creo que es bueno vivir aquí.
But this is the Reflection Pavilion.
Pero este es el Pabellón de Reflexión.
The name is the problem, right?
El nombre es el problema, ¿verdad?
It's easy.
Es fácil.
To suffer a loss in one place, but make a gain somewhere else.
Sufrir una pérdida en un lugar, pero consigan una ganancia en otro lugar.
It's not too late.
No es demasiado tarde.
Let's call it Feiwan Pavilion. [*Feiwan: Not too late]
Llamémoslo Pabellón Feiwan. [* Feiwan: No demasiado tarde]
Right.
Correcto.
My scar cream
Mi crema para cicatrices
will be called Feiwan Cream.
se llamará Feiwan Cream.
Your Ladyship.
Su señoría.
Why don't we
¿Por qué no
move back to the Rose Garden?
vuelve al Jardín de las Rosas?
The Rose Garden
El Jardín de las Rosas
is where the First Lady lives.
es donde vive la Primera Dama.
This is a place
Este es un lugar
for repentant people.
para gente que se arrepiente.
Besides,
Además,
His Lordship has often come to you lately.
su Señoría ha venido a menudo a usted últimamente.
We should
Deberíamos
stay closer to him.
quédate cerca de él.
That's right.
Es cierto.
Nanny Liu.
Niñera Liu.
Go back and tell him
Vuelve y dile
that since he's been
que desde que
getting better lately,
mejorando últimamente,
he doesn't need to come here so often.
no necesita venir aquí tan a menudo.
Your Lordship.
Su Señoría.
These are...
Estos son...
Her Ladyship asked me
Su señoría me pidió
to bring these things here.
para traer estas cosas aquí.
She said
Ella dijo
the pillow is sagging because you slept on it,
la almohada está empinada porque dormiste en ella,
so it's yours now.
así que es tuyo ahora.
Take it away.
Llévalo.
Yes.
Sí.
What else did she do?
¿Qué más hizo?
She changed the name of Reflection Pavilion
Cambió el nombre de Pabellón de Reflexión
to Feiwan Pavilion
a Pabellón Feiwan
and the name of Scar Recovering Cream
y el nombre de Scar Recovering Cream
to Feiwan Cream.
a Feiwan Cream.
Feiwan Pavilion.
Pabellón Feiwan.
It's never too late
Nunca es demasiado tarde
to cherish the time.
apreciar el tiempo.
That's
Es
an interesting name.
un nombre interesante.
Your Lordship, there is one more thing.
Su Señoría, hay una cosa más.
Go ahead.
Sigue.
Her Ladyship wants to spend
Su señoría quiere gastar
100 taels of silver
100 taels de plata
to entertain
entretener a
all the wealthy young ladies in the capital.
todas las chicas ricas en la capital.
But she thought it was too much trouble.
Pero ella pensaba que era demasiado problema.
Why does she
¿Por qué
want to do it with her own money now?
quiere hacerlo con su propio dinero ahora?
She said she would use her own money
Ella dijo que usaría su propio dinero
to mingle with those aristocrats
para mezclar con esos aristócratas
and sell them her products.
y les vende sus productos.
The money she earns
El dinero que gana
will be all hers.
será toda ella.
She knows how to do the math.
Sabe como hacer las cuentas.
But with her reputation,
Pero con su reputación,
who will come?
quién vendrá?
General Nie and his family
El General Nie y su familia
will arrive in the capital soon.
llegará pronto a la capital.
Summer stars, autumn night
♪ estrellas de verano, noche de otoño ♪
Who is wandering under the moon in my heart
♪ Quién está vagando debajo de la luna en mi corazón ♪
The deepest story with the shallowest goodbye
♪ La historia más profunda con la más superficial adiós ♪
After passing by, I can only meet you in my dream
♪ Tras pasar, solo puedo verte en mi sueño ♪
The wind can't breeze the long street of time
♪ El viento no puede brisa la larga calle de tiempo ♪
The burning yearning will never cool
♪ El anhelo ardiente nunca se enfriará ♪
Two hearts meet again foreshadowing love
♪ Dos corazones se encuentran de nuevo el amor anunciado ♪
How can I describe it when we look into each other's eyes
♪ ¿Cómo lo puedo describir cuando nos fijamos en los ojos del otro ♪
Take a life time to write the story
♪ Tome un tiempo de vida para escribir la historia ♪
Together with you
♪ Junto contigo ♪
Company you
♪ Compañía contigo ♪
Just for your glance and smile
♪ Solo por tu mirada y sonrisa ♪
The first promise means the forever love
♪ La primera promesa significa el amor para siempre ♪
Fireworks all over the sky light up your night
♪ fuegos artificiales por todo el cielo enciende tu noche ♪
Take a life time
♪ Tome un tiempo de vida ♪
To write the story with you gradually
♪ Para escribir la historia contigo gradualmente ♪
Just like this
♪ Al igual que esto ♪
Our love goes on and on
♪ Nuestro amor continúa y sigue ♪
The day we first met, the year when we get old
♪ El día que nos vimos por primera vez, el año en que envejecemos ♪
My heart and my love will never vanish
♪ Mi corazón y mi amor nunca desaparecerán ♪